This is just one of many examples. Ukraine has been suffering from Russian propaganda and fake news for four years now, but Russia is not the only player in this space. Fake news is happening all around the world. We all know about fake news. We see it and read it all the time. But the thing about fake news is that we don't always know what is fake and what is real, but we base our decisions on facts we get from the press and social media. When facts are false, decisions are wrong. A lot of people stop believing anyone at all and this is even more dangerous. They easily become prey to populists in elections, or even take up arms. Fake news is not only bad for journalism. It's a threat for democracy and society. Four years ago, unmarked soldiers entered the Crimean Peninsula, and at the same time, Russian media was going crazy with fake news about Ukraine. So a group of journalists, including me, started a website to investigate this fake news. We called it StopFake. The idea was simple: take a piece of news, check it with verifiable proof like photos, videos and other strong evidence. If it turns out to be fake, we put it on our website. Now, StopFake is an informational hub which analyzes propaganda in all its phases. We have 11 language versions, we have millions of views, We have taught more than 10,000 people how to distinguish true from false. And we teach fact checkers all around the world. StopFake has uncovered more than 1,000 fakes about Ukraine. We've identified 18 narratives created using this fake news, such as Ukraine is a fascist state, a failed state, a state run by a junta who came to power as a result of a coup d'état. We proved that it's not bad journalism; it's a deliberate act of misinformation. Fake news is a powerful weapon in information warfare, but there is something we can do about it. We all have smartphones. When we see something interesting, it's often automatic. We just click and pass it along. But how can you not be a part of fake news? First, if it's too dramatic, too emotional, too clickbait, then it's very likely that it isn't true. The truth is boring sometimes. (Laughter) Manipulations are always sexy. They are designed to captivate you. Do your research. This is the second point, very simple. Look at other sites. Check out alternative news sources. Google names, addresses, license plates, experts and authors. Don't just believe, check. It's the only way to stop this culture of fake news. This information warfare is not only about fake news. Our society depends on trust: trust in our institutions, in science, trust in our leaders, trust in our news outlets. And it's on us to find a way to rebuild trust, because fake news destroys it. So ask yourself, what have you lost your faith in?
Este es solo uno de muchos ejemplos. Ucrania ha sufrido de la propaganda y las falsas noticias rusas desde hace ya cuatro años, pero Rusia no es la única que lo está haciendo. Las noticias falsas se esparcen por todo el mundo. Todos hemos oído noticias falsas, las vemos y leemos todo el tiempo. Pero el problema de las noticias falsas es que no siempre sabemos qué es falso y qué es real, pero nuestras decisiones se basan en hechos que recibimos de la prensa y de las redes sociales. Cuando los datos son falsos, las decisiones son erradas. Muchos empiezan a dudar de todo y esto es aún más peligroso. Se vuelven presas fáciles para los populistas en las elecciones, o incluso toman las armas. Las noticias falsas no son malas solo para el periodismo, son una amenaza para la sociedad y la democracia. Hace cuatro años, soldados sin distintivos entraron a la península de Crimea y en el mismo momento, los medios rusos enloquecían con noticias falsas sobre Ucrania. Así que un grupo de periodistas, del que yo era parte, creó un sitio web para investigar estas noticias falsas. Lo llamamos "StopFake". La idea era simple: tomar una noticia, buscar pruebas de su veracidad, como fotos, videos y otras evidencias concretas, y si resulta ser falsa, la ponemos en nuestro sitio web. StopFake es ahora un centro de información que analiza propaganda en todas sus fases. Tenemos versiones en 11 idiomas y tenemos millones de visitas. Hemos enseñado a más de 10 000 personas cómo distinguir lo verdadero de lo falso y hemos entrenado a verificadores de información en todo el mundo. StopFake ha desenmascarado más de mil noticias falsas sobre Ucrania. Hemos identificado 18 historias creadas a través de noticias falsas. Por ejemplo: Ucrania es un estado fascista, un estado fallido, un estado dirigido por una junta que llegó al poder por un golpe de estado. Hemos demostrado que no es mal periodismo, es un acto deliberado de desinformación. Las noticias falsas son un arma poderosa en la guerra de la información, pero podemos hacer algo al respecto. Todos tenemos teléfonos inteligentes. Cuando vemos algo interesante, a menudo es automático. Solo damos clic y lo compartimos. Pero, ¿cómo podemos evitar ser parte de las falsas noticias? Primero, si es demasiado dramático, demasiado emocional, demasiado sensacionalista, entonces es muy probable que no sea cierto. La verdad es aburrida, a veces. (Risas) La manipulación siempre es sexy, está diseñada para cautivarnos. Investiguen Uds. mismos. Ese es el segundo punto, muy simple. Revisen otros sitios. Busquen fuentes de noticias alternativas. Busquen nombres, direcciones, matrículas, expertos y ofertas en Google. No crean solamente, verifiquen. Es la única forma de frenar esta cultura de noticias falsas. Esta guerra de información no se trata solo de noticias falsas. Nuestra sociedad depende de la confianza: confianza en nuestras instituciones, en la ciencia, confianza en nuestros líderes, confianza en nuestros medios informativos. Y depende de nosotros encontrar la forma de restaurar esa confianza, porque las noticias falsas la destruyen. Entonces, pregúntense: ¿En qué han perdido la fe?
Where has trust been ruined for you? And what are you going to do about it? Thank you. (Applause)
¿Cómo se ha arruinado su confianza? Y, ¿qué van a hacer al respecto? Gracias. (Aplausos)